Guide to the Peter Goin Photographs, 1991-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Peter Goin photographs 1991-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Goin, Peter, 1951-
6.0 linear feet Extent: 447 Items
Photographer and professor of art at the University of Nevada, Reno, whose work has focused on the interactions between humans and nature, particularly human-altered landscapes. Collection consists of black and white photographs, negatives, and color photographs on the theme of the interactions and the connections between people and the natural world, and the way people manage, perceive, and represent "nature." The images were taken by photographer Peter Goin from 1991-1992 while he was Artist-In-Residence at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. They were shot in various locations, predominantly in North and South Carolina and Virginia, but also in Alabama, Georgia, central Florida, Arizona, California, and Tennessee. There is also one image from Nevada. A selection of these images was published in the book, Humanature, published by University of Texas Press in 1996, and the project also generated a traveling exhibit by the same name. The photographs often depict altered and artificial landscapes featuring beaches, canals, farm fields, rivers, managed forests, prescribed burns and reforestation sites, zoos, and other places. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts, Duke University.
goinpeter
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research; however, photocopying is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Peter Goin Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 1992-1994.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of black and white photographs, negatives, and color photographs on the theme of the interactions and the connections between people and the natural world, and the way people manage, perceive, and represent "nature." The images were taken by photographer Peter Goin from 1991-1992 while he was Artist-In-Residence at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. They were shot in various locations, predominantly in North and South Carolina and Virginia, but also in Alabama, Georgia, central Florida, Arizona, California, and Tennessee. There is also one image from Nevada. A selection of these images was published in the book, Humanature, published by University of Texas Press in 1996, and the project also generated a traveling exhibit by the same name. The photographs often depict altered and artificial landscapes featuring beaches, canals, farm fields, rivers, managed forests, prescribed burns and reforestation sites, zoos, and other places. Locations in North Carolina include Durham, the NC Zoological Park, Duke Forest, the Carnivore Preservation Trust, Outer Banks beaches, the Chatooga and Nantahala Rivers, and the mountains near Highlands, NC.
Color prints are 16x20" in size; black and white working prints are 8x10". The 4x5" negatives have been numbered sequentially from N1-N126 (some numbers absent) and the matching prints have been numbered accordingly. There are also "orphan" photographs and negatives numbered: CB31, CG32, N135, N136, N139, N141, N145, N149, N150, N160, N162, N163, N165. There are also a few images not found in the collection but which have captions in a notebook of information assembled by the photographer; these are given at the end of the collectioon guide. The full text for all captions as well as additional information about the project can be found in the notebook pages housed in Box 5.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts, Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
Organized in series by format: Negatives, Prints, and Papers.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Goin, Peter, 1951-; Environment (Art).; Environmental management -- Pictorial works; Landscape photography -- Exhibitions; Nature -- effect of human beings on; People and nature -- Pictorial works; Reclamation of land; Alabama -- Pictorial works; Arizona -- Pictorial works; California -- Pictorial works; Florida -- Pictorial works; Georgia -- Pictorial works; North Carolina -- Pictorial works; South Carolina -- Pictorial works; Tennessee -- Pictorial works; Virginia -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Negatives; Color photographs
Contents of Collection
- Negatives Series, 1991-1992, (1 box; 147 4x5" negatives)
  Contains a mostly complete collection of negatives taken of various locations documenting the interaction of humans and nature. While a large majority of the collection's black and white and color prints have corresponding negatives, about ten of these corresponding negatives are absent. The full text and identifying numbers for all captions as well as additional information about the project can be found in the notebook pages housed in Box 5.
  [Original negatives are restricted to use. Whenever possible, corresponding prints should be used. For more information, please contact a reference archivist.]
  - Negatives N1-N46, N48-N60, N62A-N75C, N78-N85, N87, N89-N94, N96, N98-101, N103-N111, N113-N118, N120-N126, N135L-N136R, N139, N141, N145-N145A, N149-N150, N160, N162-N163, N165, CB31, CG32 (Box 1)
- Prints Series, 1991-1992, (5 boxes; 259 8x10" prints)
  Corresponding negative numbers are marked on reverse side of prints. There are several prints with identification numbers CB31 and CG32. Original captions have been retained; ellipses indicate additional text in long captions that has not been included. The full text for all captions as well as additional information about the project can be found in the notebook pages housed in Box 5.
  - Black and White Working Prints, (3 boxes; 146 8x10" prints)
    - Horsepasture River near Highlands, NC: Abandoned and water-reclaimed road, national forest, N1 (Box 2)
    - Audubon Swamp near Charleston, SC..., N2 (Box 2)
    - Hollyberry Lake, NC: Overgrown and abandoned spillway near Highlands, NC, N3 (Box 2)
    - Hollyberry Lake, NC: Overflow drain at lake near Highlands, NC, N4 (Box 2)
    - Man-made flies, N5 (Box 2)
    - Duke Forest: Overgrown erosion gully, N6 (Box 2)
    - Artificial sand dune with fan at North Carolina Museum of Life and Science, N7 (Box 2)
    - Outdoor "toilet" along Horsepasture River, N8 (Box 2)
    - Tulip poplar monoculture established after clear-cutting national forest near Highlands, NC, N9 (Box 2)
    - Cut tree and overgrown stump near bridge to Horsepasture River, NC, N10 (Box 2)
    - Fabric-draped tree along Horsepasture River, NC, N11 (Box 2)
    - Human-made tree for North Carolina Zoological Park, made by zoo designer Louis Bradley..., N12 (Box 2)
      (2 prints)
    - Man-made rocks at black bear exhibit, NC Zoological Park, N13 (Box 2)
    - Man-made armature for rocks at wolf landscape, NC Zoological Park (see N116), N14 (Box 2)
    - Future site of prairie dog landscape at NC Zoological Park, N15 (Box 2)
    - Albino rainbow trout: Walhalla National Fish Hatchery and the US Fish and Wildlife Service, Department of the Interior, N16 (Box 2)
    - Stop sign and kudzu covered trees in winter with approaching winter storm near Georgia-NC boundary, N17 (Box 2)
    - Abandoned and overgrown road three miles from Chatooga River, NC, N18 (Box 2)
    - This creek is measured and drains into the Chatooga River, NC, N19 (Box 2)
    - Students in Parks and Recreation class from Clemson University..., N20 (Box 2)
    - Firewood Tree Totem at secluded creek near Transylvania County Line, NC, N21 (Box 2)
    - [uncaptioned], N22 (Box 2)
    - Black walkway across Nantahala River, NC, N23 (Box 2)
    - River markers, Nantahala River, NC, N24 (Box 2)
    - Dry Falls, NC (near Highlands): Falls and Fence, N25 (Box 2)
    - Boundary marked trees near Highlands, NC, N26 (Box 2)
    - Man-made falls at Sequoyah Lake and dam, Highlands, NC..., N27 (Box 2)
    - Plastic fern grove in national forest near Highlands, NC, N28 (Box 2)
    - ...Two views of helicopter stocking of Chatooga River...stocking one year old rainbow trout..., N29A-B (Box 2)
    - Judaculla Rock covered with gazebo near East Laport, NC..., N30 (Box 2)
    - ..."H-7 shack" on Howard Creek within the Bad Creek Hydro-electric power station in North Carolina...two Duke Power employees, John Garton (right) and Allen Nicholson (left) observe..., N31 (Box 2)
    - Revegetation field called Spoil Area 5 within the Bad Creek Power station. It is planted with sawtooth oaks, red and white clover, and sericea..., N32 (Box 2)
    - "Caution-Avoid" sign at Joyce Kilmer Memorial Forest, N33 (Box 2)
    - ...Two hunters, Eric Sellers (left) and Niel Morgan are waiting for their dogs to return after hunting "bear and boar" in Joyce Kilmer Memorial Forest, N34 (Box 2)
    - Chimp climbing tree (see N12), N35 (Box 2)
    - Carving, or weathering, man-made rock, N36 (Box 2)
    - Human-made tornado at NC Museum of Life and Science..., N37 (Box 2)
    - Beach wall, Ft. Fisher, south of Kure Beach, NC (man-made rocks, including brick debris, concrete), N38 (Box 2)
    - Sea wall, south of Wrightsville Beach, NC..., N39 (Box 2)
    - End of the road, ocean damage north of Surf City, NC, N40 (Box 2)
    - Abandoned pier building, ocean damage, north of Surf City, NC, N41 (Box 2)
    - Lenny Olivaros and Juan Angel Gomez planting a water oak (quercus nigra) in waterfowl area next to human-made swamp at NC Zoological Park, N42 (Box 2)
    - Lenny Olivaros (L) and Juan Angel Gomez carrying (planting) Laurel Oak (quercus laurifolia) into waterfowl area next to human-made swamp at NC Zoological Park. Robert Evans, the project foreman, is directing, N43 (Box 2)
    - Bob McCandless and helpers are "shooting" cement onto rock forms in the desert area of the North American Landscape section of the NC Zoological Park, N44 (Box 2)
    - Numbered Trees in Duke Forest (rainy day)..., N45 (Box 2)
    - Sign in Duke Forest..., N46 (Box 2)
    - Arbor at Roanoke Island within Ft. Raleigh National Historic Site..., N48 (Box 2)
    - (Sand colored) large sandbags positioned to act as seabreak in front of Cape Hatteras lighthouse, N49 (Box 2)
    - Discarded Christmas trees in parking lot of picnic area at Ft. Macon..., N50 (Box 3)
    - "Shooting" cement onto artificial rocks at grizzly exhibit at NC Zoo ("unshot" rocks in foreground), N51 (Box 3)
    - Welding work (inside armature) for rocks at grizzly exhibit..., N52 (Box 3)
    - Orange fences mark "nature areas" at NC Zoo, N53 (Box 3)
    - Four women who work at the NC Zoo in the design department..., N54 (Box 3)
    - Human-made Peregrine Falcon nest within a steep rock face at Lake Jocassee reservoir area, upstate South Carolina...includes three views...the nest and two views from different distances of the workmen, N55 and N55A-B (Box 3)
      (3 prints)
    - ...These two photographs are from the town of Ellenton. The front steps of the school are still visible under the growth. The front porch of Dr. Lucius Bailey's house is all that remains..., N56A-B (Box 3)
    - "Wildlife Food Plot" sign from the Duke Power Company, N57 (Box 3)
    - Wild turkey, largemouth bass, wood duck, and white-tailed deer waiting for final painting and customer pick up, McKinsey Wildlife Taxidermy, Anderson, SC..., N58 (Box 3)
    - Prescribed burn of longleaf pine forest within Sandhills State Forest near Cheraw, SC, N59 (Box 3)
    - Accidental burn along roadside of longleaf pine forest within Sandhills State Forest near Cheraw, SC, N60 (Box 3)
    - Two views of wild turkey trapping operation in Florence County, SC..., N62 (Box 3)
    - ...Called the "artificial," "fake," "phony," or "dummy" deer by the public, the decoy was the direct result of more than 377 deer poaching citations..., N63 (Box 3)
    - ...Called the "artificial," "fake," "phony," or "dummy" deer by the public, the decoy was the direct result of more than 377 deer poaching citations..., N64 (Box 3)
    - Numerous views of active burn conducted at Peachtree Rock Preserve by Nature Conservancy personnel in South Carolina..., N65 (Box 3)
    - Portrait of burn personnel..., N66 (Box 3)
    - The day after the prescribed burn. Originally, discarded Christmas trees were placed in this drainage area to arrest erosion, N67 (Box 3)
    - The day after the prescribed burn...working to eliminate a smoldering stump..., N68 (Box 3)
    - Hydro-seeding restored landscape. Owen Parton is using a high-pressure hose to apply fertilizer, lime, a mixture of clover and fescue grass seed with mulch, N69 (Box 3)
    - Erosion control at Coon Branch, Duke Power Co. property. Rock lined drainage designed to prevent silt from clogging the Whitewater River, N70 (Box 3)
    - Power House and Pilot Tunnel, N71 (Box 3)
    - Discharge or tail-race tunnel with human-made rock walls, Duke Power Co...., N72 (Box 3)
    - Red silt in drainage ditch, Duke Power Co., N73 (Box 3)
    - Lone tree in clear-cut area after recent reforestation effort near Emporia, Virginia, N74 (Box 3)
    - ...Numerous views of Virginia Beach City beach restoration and maintenance, 1992. Beach site is at Atlantic and 35th Street access..., N75B-C (Box 3)
    - Artificial landscape at 22nd and Pacific Avenue (Jungle Golf), Virginia Beach, VA, N78 (Box 3)
    - Walk-ramp and rain gauge at flow-through marsh, east side of Pool B, Kissimmee River system, N79 (Box 3)
    - The Kissimmee River channel denied water flow to the oxbow portions of the historic (or prior) river..., N80 (Box 3)
    - Weir #3, Kissimmee River..., N81 (Box 3)
    - Hunter's camp and hog's foot at Oak Hammock along the historic section of the Kissimmee River, N82 (Box 3)
    - Rope swing at hunter's camp, Oak Hammock, Kissimmee River, N83 (Box 3)
    - ...Weir #2 in front of "Charlie" bombing range..., N84L-R (Box 3)
      (3 triptych prints)
    - Camp Yahoo north near Weir #3 along Kissimmee River..., N85 (Box 3)
    - Dave Darrow, Wildlife Biologist, at the Highway 60 check station for the Three Lakes Wildlife Management Area bordering Lake Kissimmee, central Florida..., N87 (Box 3)
    - ...Recreational boats at Silver Glen Springs, Ocala National Forest and Lake George, central Florida (near Orlando), N89L-R (Box 3)
    - Parking area construction for public beach access #4 Onslow County, NC..., N92 (Box 3)
    - 24 Hour dredging and beach restoration operation, Topsail Beach, NC, N93 (Box 3)
    - "Buried Telephone Cable" flags along Topsail Beach, NC, N94 (Box 3)
    - ...Hamster courtesy of Pet Mania, Durham, NC, N96 (Box 3)
    - Best general view of North Potato Creek Falls and cement truck, Ducktown, Tennessee, N98 (Box 3)
    - ...Early reforestation trees near Ducktown, N99 (Box 3)
    - ...Tennessee Chemical Company mining tower view of landscape looking towards Copperhill, Tennessee. Restoration pine now covers the landscape, N100L-R (Box 4)
      (2 diptych prints)
    - The Burra Burra Mine caved in fifty years ago, leaving a massive (and dangerous) water-filled pit..., N101 (Box 4)
    - Burnt kudzu vines and telephone wires, Copperhill, TN, N103 (Box 4)
    - Dormant kudzu covered landscape, Copperhill, TN, N104 (Box 4)
    - Roadkill. The possum, the only marsupial in North America..., N105 (Box 4)
    - Male Eld Deer (Thai) on urine collection platform, National Zoo Conservation and Research Center, Front Royal, Virginia, N106 (Box 4)
    - Male Eld Deer (David) with Linwood Williamson, Wildlife Technician, in outdoor yard, National Zoo Conservation and Research center, Front Royal, Virginia, N107 (Box 4)
    - ...This photograph documents one of the artificially inseminated Eld Deer (Vanessa) on the weighing platform with Linwood Willimason and Dennis Hosack..., N108 (Box 4)
    - ...This photograph documents young binturongs (Arctictis binturong, Southeast Asia) eating fruit against the chain link fence..., N109 (Box 4)
    - Nancy Schonwalter, member of the core staff at CPT, frames a jaguar..., N110 (Box 4)
    - The Orange County, NC jail was moved to the carnivore trust's grounds to provide the required cage strength for Declaudine, a Malayan Sun Bear..., N111 (Box 4)
    - Dr. Michael Bleyman, founder of the Carnivore Preservation Trust, plays with Romeo and two female tigers, Marci and Charlotte..., N113 (Box 4)
    - Overgrown black leopard cage at CPT, N114 (Box 4)
    - Feeding fruit to tayra (Galera barbara)..., N115 (Box 4)
    - Rock nearly completed at Zoo (see N14), N116 (Box 4)
    - Drain in swamp at NC Zoo, N117 (Box 4)
    - Steve Runnfeldt, Assistant Design Technician, mixing paint for rocks at desert area, NC Zoo, N118 (Box 4)
    - Human-made rocks, NC Zoo (see N51), N120 (Box 4)
    - Rephotographs of Virginia Beach during Memorial Day weekend: (letters coincide with N75A-C), N121A-C (Box 4)
    - View looking south from top of Thunderbird Hotel, Virginia Beach, during Memorial Day weekend, N122 (Box 4)
    - Kudzu and wire along Intersate Highway 40 west of Durham, NC, N123 (Box 4)
    - ...Kudzu and snake(s) along NC Highway 421 west of Winston-Salem, N124L-R (Box 4)
    - Geer Cemetery 1877-1944, Durham, NC, N125A-B (Box 4)
    - Kissimmee River Research Project Model Study at the University of California at Berkeley, CA...Roger Manley poses to indicate the scale, N126 (Box 4)
    - ...This company-owned residential district, now abandoned, was named the Stargo townsite..., N135L-R (Box 4)
    - ...The Clifton-Morenci Pit, one of the largest open-pit copper mines in North America..., N136L-R (Box 4)
    - A tailings plateau near Miami, Arizona, N139 (Box 4)
    - Pseudoliths along road near Clifton, Arizona..., N141 (Box 4)
    - Waterfall at Pinal Creek, N145 (Box 4)
    - Pipes at Pinal Creek at Globea dn Miami, Arizona, N145A (Box 4)
    - ...Three-acre, enclosed ecological system in the foothills of the Santa Catalina Mountains north of Tucson Arizona...Biosphere 2..., N149 (Box 4)
    - The Pacific Ocean at Cabrillo National Monument at San Diego, California, N150 (Box 4)
    - Workers from the Los Angeles Conservation Corps use a water-blaster to clean graffiti off rocks along a tributary to the West fork of the San Gabriel River in the Angeles National Forest..., N160 (Box 4)
    - Painted rocks and engraved trees along the West fork of the San Gabriel River in the Angeles National Forest, California, N162 (Box 4)
    - Toxic Nation, Angeles National Forest, N163 (Box 4)
    - Heavy smog over the Angeles National Forest near Los Angeles, California, N165 (Box 4)
    - Watering the sand at Palm Desert, California, CB31 (Box 4)
    - A boy in red fishes in the stagnant water on the other side of the Rye Patch Dam in north-central Nevada after the final 800-acre feet of water was drained for irrigation, 1992, CG32 (Box 4)
  - Color Prints Subseries, (2 boxes; 113 16x20" color prints)
    Color prints are marked on reverse with corresponding negative numbers. Captions for images found only in the color series and not in the black and white prints series are given below. Otherwise, captions for color prints duplicated in the black and white prints series are found there.
    - Color Prints N2, N5-N6, N8, N10-N11, N14, N16-N21, N24, N28, N29A-N36, N39-N42, N44-N46, N48, N50, N53-N56, N58, N60, N62-N64 (captions are listed in black and white prints series) (Box 5)
    - Numerous views of active burn conducted at Peachtree Rock Preserve by Nature Conservancy personnel in South Carolina..., N65 (Box 6)
      (5 prints)
    - Color Prints N72-N74 (captions for these prints are listed in black and white prints series) (Box 6)
    - ...Numerous views of Virginia Beach City beach restoration and maintenance, 1992. Beach site is at Atlantic and 35th Street access..., 75A-C (Box 6)
    - Color Prints N79, N81-N82, N84-N85, N87, N89L-N89R (captions are listed in black and white prints series) (Box 6)
    - Boy Scout Troops 401 and 447 earning their canoe merit badges at Buck Lake, Ocala National Forest, Florida..., N90 (Box 6)
    - Public beach access structure north of Surf City in Onslow County, NC, N91 (Box 6)
    - (caption is listed in black and white prints series), N92 (Box 6)
    - 24 hour dredging and beach restoration operation, Topsail Beach, NC, N93 (Box 6)
    - Color Prints N94, N96, N98-N101, N103-N111, N113-N117, N121C, N124L-N124R, N126, N135L-N136R, N139, N141, N145-N145A, N149-N150, N160, N162-N163, N165, CB31, CG32 (captions are listed in black and white prints series) (Box 6)
- Papers Series, 1991-1994, (1 folder)
  Houses pages from a notebook of information assembled by the photographer, which describes the project "Humanature," and is accompanied by a full list of captions. Captions given in the section below are taken from notebook, and represent images from Humanature that are not in the collection.
  - Notebook pages, undated, (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Print captions listed in notebook that do not have existing prints or negatives in the collection:
    - Numerous views of Virginia Beach City beach restoration. These views represent the dredging and bulldozing near 7th along the Boardwalk..., N76 (Box 5)
    - Beach restoration project for Virginia Beach City; Lynnhaven Inlet Sand Stockpile and truck loading operation, N77 (Box 5)
    - Pool A, small oxbow denied running water after the channel was completed in 1971..., N86 (Box 5)
    - Two-spot West African Palm Civet poses for the camera..., N112 (Box 5)